Guide to the Edward Livingston Wells Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Edward Livingston Wells papers
1854-1870
MS 1170
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
Nearly half the papers are made up of the texts of Edward Livingston Wells' sermons and a series of lectures on Genesis. The remainder consists of notes (in French) made while he was a student at the Protestant Theological Seminary in Montauban, France.
Wells, Edward Livingston, 1834-1880
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lewis P. Curtis, 1944.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Edward Livingston Wells Papers are contained in one box and were given to Yale University by Lewis Perry Curtis in 1944.
The Papers primarily consist of lectures on Genesis (folders 2-10), sermons (folders 11-13), and student notes (folders 14-23). The lectures on Genesis I:1-31 were given between January and March 1856. Manuscripts of five sermons are included, among them Wells' first sermon, written in French, while he was attending the Protestant Theological Seminary of Montauban, France, and an anniversary sermon from Matthew VII:20. The student notes are all written in French and cover religious topics.
For additional information on the life of Edward Livingston Wells see the Lewis Perry Curtis Family Papers, Manuscript Group Number 587, Series IV.
Biographical / Historical
Edward Livingston Wells was born in Columbia, South Carolina, in 1834. He studied theology in Pau, France and graduated with high honors. Returning to the United States, he began preaching at a Congregational church in Plainvill, Connecticut. He moved to the Episcopal church in 1859 and in 1860, was ordained to the priesthood. He would also preach in Louisville, Kentucky, Pittsfield, Massachusetts, and Southport, Connecticut. In this latter town, he and his wife, Mary Huder Hughes, had several children. He died in New Milford, Connecticut, in 1880.
France; Sermons; Clergy; Wells, Edward Livingston, 1834-1880; Episcopal Church -- Connecticut; Episcopal Church -- Massachusetts
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Lectures on Genesis I:1-31, 1856 January 6-March 6 (Box 1, Folder 2 - 10)
  - Sermons
    - First sermon, [1857?] (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Matthew VII:20, 1870 March (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Matthew VII:13-14, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - John III:3, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Psalm XIV:2-3 (fragment), undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Student notes
    - "Morale", 1854-1855 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Authenticitédes Evangiles, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Vie de Jésus, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Authenticité de l'Evangile salon St, Jean (incomplete), undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Histoire de la morale chrétienne, undated (Box 1, Folder 18 - 21)
    - "Influence morale de la Renaissance", undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - "Les Paraboles", undated (Box 1, Folder 23)